Space debris, refuse generated as a result of
space development, is a very serious threat.
（ナレーション）宇宙開発の
結果として出た廃棄物―
スペースデブリは
実は とても危険な存在です
This is a story of 2076, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
これは 2076年―
宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
（ラジオ）しばらく
お目にかかりませんでしたが―
So I say, "I haven't seen you for
a while, where have you been?"
どちらのほうへ
おいででございますかと―
これに向こうが小用で
海岸のほうにとでも言ったら…
So when he says he was on
a business trip on the beach,
Hoshino
...I say I say to him, "No wonder you look
so tanned, it's because of the sea breeze."
（ハルコの鼻歌）
（戸の開閉音）
I'm home.
（ハチマキ）ただいま
（戸の開閉音）
（ハルコ）ハチかい？
That you, Hachi?
You're hopeless. Just saying that you'll
be home today doesn't tell me anything.
あんたって子は―
“今日 帰る”だけじゃ
分かんないでしょ
何時の便かくらい…
At least tell me when
your flight...
（ハルコ）あら
Oh, my.
Coworkers of mine.
（ハチマキ）会社の同僚
うちが成田(なりた)の
すぐ近くだって言ったら―
When I told them we lived near Narita,
they said they wanted to come visit.
遊びに来たいって
Good afternoon.
（ユーリ）こんにちは
I hope we're not imposing.
（タナベ）お邪魔します
♪～
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
♪光が向かう場所へ
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
♪フロンティアへ
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
Geez, I didn't want to take a vacation,
but our ship got destroyed.
（ハチマキ）
…ったく 休暇なんて―
Phase 13
Scenery with a Rocket
取りたくなかったん
だけど―
俺たちの船が
壊れちまってさ
お前 何かやったのかい？
Did you do something
to it?
（ハチマキ）
俺じゃねえよ
It wasn't me.
Our captain
rammed it into something.
船長自ら 体当たりさせて
あっ ひょっとして
この間 ニュースでやってたやつ？
Oh, you don't mean that scare that was
on the news a while ago, do you?
Yes, the Space Defense Front incident.
はい 宇宙防衛戦線の事件です
船は
なくなってしまいましたが―
We lost our ship, but we managed
to foil the terrorists' plan.
テロリストの作戦を
防げたんですから
Yuri-san, your Japanese is excellent.
Where did you learn it?
ユーリさん 日本語 上手ね
どちらで勉強されたの？
ああ 妻が日本人でした
My wife was Japanese.
Was?
（ハルコ）でした？
She passed away. It was eight years ago.
死にました ８年前です
（ハルコ）
あら 悪いこと聞いちゃったわね
Oh, I'm sorry I brought it up.
No, that is all right.
いやあ 大丈夫です
そのことは もう大丈夫
I am okay with it now.
（飛行音）
（タナベ）ん？
はっ…
ユーリさん タナベさん 伏せて
Yuri-san! Tanabe-san! Take cover!
（タナベ）あっ
（ユーリ）えっ？ あっ
（ハチマキ）どうした？
What's wrong?
ぐっ があーっ
（九太郎(きゅうたろう)）危ねえ 危ねえ
よその家じゃなくて よかった
Oh, man, that was close!
I'm glad it didn't hit a neighbor's house!
（タナベ）先輩 先輩！
Senpai! Senpai!
Say something, Senpai!
しっかりしてください 先輩
（九太郎）
しかし まっすぐ飛ばねえなあ
Damn, this thing totally
refuses to fly straight.
Maybe there's a problem with
the gimbal adjustment, too...
ジンバルの調整も悪かったかなあ
九太郎！
Kyutaro! How many times do I have to tell you
to launch your rockets down at the beach?!
ロケットは海岸で飛ばしなさいって
何度 言わせんの！
お客様に何かあったら―
If anything happens to our guests, I'm taking
those rockets away, do you hear me?!
もう 母ちゃん
そのロケット 取り上げるからね！
What, you don't care
what happens to me?
俺は どうなってもいいのかよ
（九太郎）ん…
I did launch it
out towards the sea.
ちゃんと海のほうに飛ばしたさ
But the piece of crap gyro
isn't compatible.
ただ ジャイロと
いまいち相性が悪いんだ
こんにゃろう
１年ぶりの兄貴に これが挨拶か
You little bastard! You haven't seen me
for a year, and this is how you say hello?!
Oh, you're back, bro?
あっ 帰ってたのか 兄ちゃん
お前は ずうたいばっかり
でかくなりやがって―
You might have grown some,
but these stunts of yours are still...
やるこたあ 昔っから…
変わんねえな ずうたいも
No, I guess you
haven't grown.
お前 もうすぐ 14だろ？
Aren't you nearly 14?
Screw you! Leave me alone!
（九太郎）
う… うるせーや 放っとけ！
うっ… ああ…
先輩！
Senpai!
Are you all right?! Senpai!
大丈夫ですか？ 先輩
I suppose it's
in their blood.
（ハルコ）血筋ってやつかしらね
ほら あの子の父親も兄貴も
宇宙飛行士でしょう？
You see, that boy's father and big brother
are both astronauts.
Huh? Their father is
an astronaut, too?
（タナベ）えっ お父さんも
宇宙飛行士なんですか？
That's right. He didn't tell you?
（ハルコ）そうよ 聞いてない？
No, ma'am,
not a word.
（タナベ）はい 全然
（ハルコ）それとも あれかな？
Or maybe it's that
other thing.
Hachi and Kyuta were the result of us getting
lucky while we were on trips to the moon,
ハチも キュウタも―
夫婦で 月旅行してるときに
当てた子だから―
...so maybe they have
a connection to space.
宇宙に縁があるのかしら
福引きみたいに言うなよ
Don't make it sound like
a lottery drawing.
How can I put it? It's like Kyutaro
has too much energy pent up inside.
何ていうか―
勢い余っちゃってるのよね
九太郎は
まだ 13歳なんだから
そんなに焦らなくてもいいのにね
He's still only 13, so I don't see why
he has to be in such a hurry.
Where did Kyutaro-kun go?
九太郎君 どこに行ったんですか？
（ユーリ）へえ
ん？ あっ…
Oh, you are distilling seawater
and then electrolyzing it.
（ユーリ）海水を蒸留してから
電気分解するんですか
That makes you self-sufficient
as far as fuel is concerned.
燃料は 自給自足というわけですね
（九太郎）ん…
Yuri Mihairokoh.
ユーリ･ミハイロコフ
星野(ほしの)… 八郎太(はちろうた)兄さんの同僚です
I work with your brother, Hoshino Hachirota.
星野九太郎
Hoshino Kyutaro.
Your hideout is
most impressive.
（ユーリ）すごいアジトですね
I rent it from a fisherman that
I know. A thousand yen a year.
（九太郎）
知り合いの漁師さんから借りてんだ
年間 1,000円で
触っちゃ駄目だ！
Don't touch that!
それ低温だから やけどする
It's super-cooled,
so it'll burn you.
Did you make all this
by yourself?
これ みんな
自分で作ったんですか？
I swiped 'em from the scrapyard down by
the spaceport. What do you want, anyway?
宇宙港近くの廃材置き場から
盗んできた
何の用？
Oh. I had an idea regarding
your rocket.
ああ さっきの
ロケットのことなんですけど
I used to ride this when I was in high school.
（ハチマキ）
高校のときに乗ってたんだ
（タナベ）へえ
It's been sitting around for ages,
so it might not run very well.
（ハチマキ）
長いこと ほったらかしてたから
吹けが悪いかもな
You're probably having trouble with low-gravity
disorder and space lag, right?
低重力障害とか
時差ボケできついんだろ？
俺一人で行ってくるから―
I'll go by myself,
so you stay here...
お前は家に入ってていいぞ
（タナベ）先輩
- Senpai.
Do you even know
what nampura is?
ナンプラーって分かります？
あ… 野菜？
A vegetable?
ウフッ やっぱり 私も行きます
I think I'd better
go with you.
（キーボードを打つ音）
九太郎君のパソコンに―
I will copy the navigation and guidance system
that Technora uses onto your PC.
テクノーラ社が使っている
航行誘導システムをコピーします
This should make
a big difference.
これで 随分 違うはずですよ
そんなの
勝手にコピーしていいの？
Are you allowed to make
copies like that?
It is a crime. But only if someone finds out.
犯罪です バレればね
（ハチマキ）
えーっと あとは大根と
Let's see, all we need
now is a daikon.
先輩
Senpai, the ones with leaves
taste better. They're sweeter.
葉っぱがついてるやつのほうが
甘くて おいしいんですよ
（ハチマキ）へえ
Is that you, Hoshino?
（タクミ）おい 星野か？
（ハチマキ）あ？
Long time, no see!
久しぶりだなあ
Takumi, is that you? Geez, you got fat!
お前 タクミか？ 太ったなあ
いきなり そりゃないだろう
Is that any way to talk
to an old buddy?
This is a friend of mine from high school.
We used to ride our bikes together all the time.
高校のときの友達
よく２人で バイク乗り回してさ
まだ乗ってるか？
You still ride?
いやあ 車を買ったよ
ワンボックス
No, I bought a car. A mini-van.
げっ だっさ
Talk about lame...
う… うるせえな お前だって…
Hey, get off my back! It's not like you...
- Takumi?
（タクミの妻）タッ君
おしょうゆって まだ… あっ
Do we still
have soy sauce...
ああ…
こいつ 星野
This is Hoshino. You know, the old bike buddy
of mine who became an astronaut.
ほら バイク友達でさ
宇宙飛行士になったって
ああ 宇宙船を買うとか
Oh, the one who was going
to buy a spaceship!
ああ 宇宙船を買うとか
（赤ん坊の泣き声）
Sorry, sorry...
What the heck did you
tell her about me?
お前 どういう説明してんだよ
What's the big deal? It's ancient history now.
いいだろう？ 昔の話なんだから
Milk? Or pee-pee?
ミルク おしっこ？
If she's crying like this,
it must be pee-pee.
この泣き方は おしっこね
Honestly, you'll never be able
to tell the difference.
いつまでたっても
分からないんだから
あ…
ちょっと おむつ替えてくるね
I'll go change
her diaper.
（タクミ）ああ
（ハチマキ）タクミ
Sure.
Takumi.
ん？
Congratulations on
getting married, man.
結婚 おめでとう
Thanks. You're getting married,
too, right, Hoshino?
ありがとう
星野もするんだろう？ 結婚
え？
It's hard to believe that
you're settling down.
いやあ お前が落ち着くなんてな
You brought your girlfriend home
to meet your parents, right?
彼女 親に紹介しに来たんだろ？
（ハチマキ）な…
（タナベ）考えてみたら―
Now that I think about it, me being
introduced to his mother...
先輩のお母さんに
紹介されるのって…
I guess it does sort of imply
that kind of situation...
だよな
Get on!
（ハチマキ）乗れよ
I copy!
ア… アイ コピー
（ハチマキ）何だ？
What's up?
あっ いえ 何でもないです
No, it's nothing.
（ハチマキ）うっ… う…
Damn it, why did Takumi
have to say that?
（ハチマキ）タクミのやつ
余計なこと言いやがって
（タナベ）どうしよう
What am I gonna do? I shouldn't have
said that I'd stay at his house...
先輩の家に泊まるなんて
言わなきゃよかった
（発射音）
あっ？
うわあ！
先輩 ロケットです こんな近くで
Senpai, it's a rocket! And it's close, too!
Yeah, cool, isn't it?
ああ すっげえだろ？
どっかの大学の
実験らしいんだけどさ
It's probably some
college experiment.
すごい すごい
Wow, that's great!
（ハチマキ）俺も同じこと言ったよ
I said the same thing when I first
saw a launch back in high school!
高校のとき 初めて見てな
くそ！ 負けてられっか
Damn it...
I ain't gonna lose
to those guys!
Kyutaro-kun, why do you want
to become an astronaut?
九太郎君は
どうして宇宙飛行士になりたいの？
俺は 宇宙飛行士にはならないよ
I'm not gonna be
an astronaut.
Especially not a half-assed one
like my old man and my brother.
特に 親父(おやじ)や兄貴みたいな
スチャラカなのには
あ…
俺は エンジニアになるんだ
I'm gonna be
an engineer.
I'm gonna grow up fast, and go on a day trip
to Mars with a rocket that I built!
さっさと大人になって―
俺のエンジンで
火星 日帰り旅行をやってやる
フッ…
What made you decide to be
an astronaut, Yuri-san?
ユーリさんは
どうして宇宙飛行士に？
あっ？ う… うーん…
ん… あっ？
（ハチマキ）
高校のときはバイクにハマってた
I was hooked on bikes
when I was in high school.
I worked part-time and
saved up the money.
バイトして 金 ためてさ
乗っては いじり
乗っては いじりしてたよ
I'd ride and tinker,
and ride and tinker.
But when I saw a rocket go up from that hill,
I thought, "I'd rather have one of those."
けどさ
あの坂からロケットを見たとき―
あっちがいいなって
思っちまったんだ
大きくて 強くて 速くて
It was big. And powerful. And fast.
Bikes didn't seem to
measure up after that.
なんか物足りなくなってさ
And that's why you became
an astronaut?
（タナベ）それで
宇宙飛行士になったんですか？
Yeah.
（ハチマキ）ああ
（タナベ）フフッ 単純ですね
That's a simple reason.
（ハチマキ）悪(わり)いかよ
What's wrong with that?
No, it's your style.
It's just what you'd expect.
（タナベ）いえ 先輩らしいです
とっても
うっ…
足 大丈夫か？
Are your feet okay? Between the Earth's gravity
and this sand, I bet they're sore.
地球の重力で しかも砂浜って
結構 きついだろう？
（タナベ）大丈夫ですよ
セブンには遠心重力あるし
No, I'm fine. Seven has
centrifugal gravity,
...and I may be your junior up in space,
but we both lived here on Earth.
宇宙では後輩だけど―
地球で暮らした時間は
変わらないんですから… うっ
（ハチマキ）おっと
Careful!
無重力と勘違いしたんだろ？
You thought you were
in zero-G, didn't you?
Sorry about that...
すいません
うっ
あっ？
あ…
Three... Two... One...
スリー ツー ワン
イグニッション
Ignition!
Go, baby, go!
いっけえーっ！
そうだ そのままー！
That's it! Keep going!
It looks good.
What is your target altitude?
（ユーリ）
いい感じです 目標高度は？
（九太郎）対流圏突破
Through the troposphere!
（爆発音）
（ユーリ）あっ 何か取れました
（九太郎）ええっ！？
Something came off.
（九太郎･ユーリ）ああ… あ…
（九太郎）ああっ…
（ユーリ･九太郎）
わあ うわあっ あああっ…
（ハチマキ）あ？
（ハチマキ･タナベ）
うわっ ああっ…
なっ…
Oh, crap! It's gonna rust!
（九太郎）くそ！ さびる～
くっ… 九太郎 てめえ！
Kyutaro, you bastard!
あ～あ
これは もう着られませんね
I suppose I won't be
wearing this again...
あっ…
あ…
Yuri-san! You aren't hurt,
are you?
（九太郎）
ユーリさーん ケガない？
ん？
A compass?
コンパス？
大事な物？
Was it important?
いえ
No.
Do not worry about it.
気にしないでください
もともと壊れていて
使えなかったんです
It was broken to begin with. It didn't work.
（ハチマキ）
おーい ユーリも来てたのか？
Hey! You were out
here, too, Yuri?
Yes, we were launching
rockets together.
（ユーリ）ええ
一緒にロケットを飛ばしていました
（ハチマキ）ユーリがついてんなら
もっと ちゃんと飛ばしてくれよ
If you're here, Yuri, make sure
those damn things fly right!
That's twice today that I thought I was gonna die.
今日だけで
２回 死にそうになってんだ
（ユーリ）ああ すみません
Sorry about that. It looks we didn't reconfigure
the guidance commands sufficiently.
誘導コマンドが
調整不足だったみたいで
（ラジオ）
いいこと聞いちゃったね ええ？
Wasn't it nice to hear that?
They say you learn a lot from talking
to old people, and that's so true.
年寄りの話は
無駄がないって 全くだよ
もう ただで…
I mean, you can drink
without paying for it, and...
（ハチマキ）はあ…
父ちゃんより食うんじゃねえの？
Is it just me, or does
he eat more than Dad?
そうなのよ
２人だけのときも４合 炊いてんの
He certainly does. Even when it's just the
two of us, I still cook enough for four.
It makes me feel like my
cooking is appreciated.
作りがいがあるわ
おい キュウタ
飯のときぐらい その学ラン 脱げよ
C'mon, Kyuta, at least take off that
school uniform when you're eating.
大体 冬休みなのに
なんで制服 着てんだ？
Why are you wearing a uniform
during winter vacation, anyway?
It doesn't even fit you,
for crying out loud!
それ以前に
お前 体に合ってねえや ったく
袖口 折ってんじゃんかよ
You've got the sleeves
rolled up!
ああ うるせえ！
Get off my case! I'm gonna
make my body fit it!
近々 体を
制服に合わせる予定なんだよ
What are you, a noncommissioned
officer from the history books?
大昔の下士官か お前は
ねえ ユーリさんって 落語 聞く？
Say, Yuri-san, do you
listen to Rakugo?
（ユーリ）落語ですか？
Rakugo?
（ハルコ）そう
Right. Japanese traditional
comical speech.
ジャパニーズ トラディショナル
コミカルスピーチ
It sounds very interesting.
（ユーリ）面白そうですね
（ハルコ）
よかったら 一緒に行く？
Would you care to go see a show with me?
- It was broken to begin with. It didn't work.
（ハルコ）
よかったら 一緒に行く？
（ユーリ）もともと壊れていて
使えなかったんです
You'd never guess it, but I'm a huge fan.
Why would he carry something
around if it was broken?
（九太郎）
なんでそんな物 持ち歩いてんだろ
（電話の呼び出し音）
（ハチマキ）
はい 星野 何だ フィーか
Hoshino residence. Oh, it's just you, Fee.
（フィー）なんだとは失礼ね
Gee, it's nice to see you, too.
Hachi, what happened to your nose?
ハチ あんた 鼻 どうしたの？
ロケットにやられた
It got hit by a rocket.
（フィー）はあ？
（ハチマキ）
んなことはいいよ 何？
Don't worry about it. So, what's up?
I have great news.
We got ourselves a new spaceship.
（フィー）いいニュースよ
私たちの新しい宇宙船が決まったの
ピッカピカの新造船だよ
A new one, fresh out
of the wrapper!
（ハチマキ）ほんとか！？
Seriously?!
ほんとよ ほんと
Cross my heart.
まあ
宇宙を救ったヒロインだからね
Well, I am the heroine
who saved space, after all.
ご褒美ってことでしょ
It's probably my
reward for that.
よく言うぜ
Get over yourself.
映像やら スペックやらのデータを
送っておくから 見といて
I'm sending you some images
and the specs, so look 'em over.
来週から
操船シミュレーションやるから―
We're starting ship-handling simulations
next week, so tell the others.
２人にも伝えて いるんでしょ？
They're with you, right?
（ハチマキ）ああ 伝えとくよ
Yeah. I'll pass it along.
Need to ask
you something.
Well, I'll leave you
to it, then.
Need to ask
you something.
（フィー）じゃ 頼んだわよ
Need to ask
you something.
Sure. Give my best
to your husband and Al.
（ハチマキ）
ああ 旦那さんとアルに よろしく
そんじゃ また宇宙で
See you up in space.
Kyutaro, that compass...
（ハチマキ）
九太郎 お前 そのコンパスは―
ユーリの奥さんの形見だ
It belonged to
his late wife.
ああっ…
（ハチマキ）
ユーリの奥さんは宇宙で死んだんだ
Yuri's wife died
in space.
Yuri became a debris hauler
so he could find that compass,
お前の壊したコンパスは―
ユーリが
わざわざ デブリ屋になって―
...which he finally did after six years,
and you just destroyed it.
６年かけて 見つけた物なんだよ
行ってこい 今すぐ
Get out there. Right now.
He said he was going
to the beach.
海岸に行くって言ってた
Apologizing won't fix that compass,
but get out there and apologize, anyway.
謝っても どうにもならねえが
謝ってこい！
（九太郎）ああっ…
（ハチマキ）
それに お前 もうロケット やめろ
And give up on those
rockets of yours.
人に迷惑がかかる
They cause nothing
but trouble.
Space isn't the fun, happy place you think it is.
People sometimes die up there.
宇宙は お前が考えてるほど
甘かねえんだ！
It's not a game for
irresponsible little kids!
責任 取れないガキの遊びとは
違うんだよ！
（九太郎）んん… うるせえ！
Screw you!
（ガラスの割れる音）
（タナベ）あっ？
Oops, there they go.
（ハルコ）おおっ 始まった
（タナベ）ええっ？
てめえ やりやがったな
Okay, now you've
pissed me off!
口先だけの宇宙飛行士に
遊びなんて言わせねえぞ！
No astronaut who's all talk
is gonna call my rockets a game!
ガキが！
You runt! Don't get so cocky over launching
a rocket that doesn't even fly straight!
まっすぐ飛ばないロケット
上げたぐらいで いい気になんな
てめえこそ
まっすぐ目標に向かえよな
Look who's talking! You're not exactly
heading straight for your target, either!
When are you finally get
that spaceship of yours?!
いつんなったら
宇宙船 手に入れんだよ
ガ… ガキには分からねえ
大人の事情があんだよ
You've got other responsibilities when you're
an adult! A runt like you wouldn't understand!
何が大人の事情だ
怖がって待ってるだけだろうが
Adult responsibilities, my ass!
You're just
waiting because you're scared!
What do you mean,
waiting?!
待ってるって？
中途半端にカッコつけて
適当なところに落ち着いて
Sure, you talk the talk, but you settled down
and got complacent the first chance you got!
（ハチマキ）
何言ってんだ このガキ！
What would you know
about it, runt?!
ガキって言うな！
Don't call me a runt! The only thing you
ever beat me at was being born before me!
早く生まれたこと以外
取り柄 ねえくせに！
へっ
Aw, that's so cute!
People can talk all they want about
possibilities and dreams when they're kids!
止めなくていいんですか？
Shouldn't we stop them?
It'll be fine.
大丈夫 うちの男どもは
殺しても死なないのが取り柄だから
Don't talk so big,
you space garbage man!
The good thing about the men in this family
is that they don't die easily.
Now you're making fun of my job, huh?! Step outside!
はあ？
But you know what? That's a very important thing.
でもね
それはとても大事なことなのよ
- Bring it on! I'll kick your ass!
Oh...
はあ…
（ハルコ）タナベさん
いい宇宙飛行士ってのはね
Tanabe-san, you can always
spot a good astronaut.
They're the ones who come
home safe, no matter what.
必ず生きて帰ってくる人よ
あ…
（ガラスの割れる音）
（九太郎）ナメんな
Don't screw with me!
てめえみてえな
スチャラカ宇宙飛行士に―
No way is a... half-assed astronaut
like you... gonna beat me!
負けるかってんだ！
（九太郎）手ごわくなったでしょ？
He's gotten stronger,
hasn't he?
Crap... I let
my guard down.
（ハチマキ）くっそう 油断した
好きで ガキやってんじゃねえや！
I'm not a kid because I wanna be one!
Yuri-san!
ユーリさーん
（ユーリ）あっ…
Oh, my. What is the matter?
Are you planning a nighttime launch?
あれ？ どうしたの？
夜間打ち上げ？
その… あの… コンパス
Um... About your compass...
（ユーリ）うん…
Just now, I was reminiscing
about something.
今 ちょっと
思い出してたんですけど―
Back when I was 20 or so, I had many things on
my mind, and I wandered all over the Earth.
私は 二十歳(はたち)くらいのころ
思うところがあって―
地球中を
ブラブラしていたことがあるんです
あっ？
I did not know where to direct my energy.
It was because I was young.
エネルギーの使い道が
分からなかったんですね
若かったから
It was not only that. There were many other
things that I did not understand.
それだけじゃない
分からないことは
他にもたくさんありました
自分は何者なんだろう
What is the "self"? What is the "other"?
他者とは何だろう
何がいいことで
何が悪いことなんだろう
What does "good" mean? What does "evil" mean?
What is space? What is the Earth?
宇宙って何だろう
地球って何だろう
目からうろこの落ちる瞬間が
来るのを期待しながら―
I walked and walked, hoping
that there would be an instant...
...when the scales would
fall from my eyes.
結構 歩きました
Having something that is beyond doubt
is a wonderful thing, is it not?
疑いようのないものを
持ってるのって―
すばらしいことだと思いませんか？
フッ…
私は 疑問ばかり持ってたから
それを確証に変えたかったんです
I had nothing but questions, so I wanted
to turn them into certainty.
そんな感じで
ブラついていたら―
And so, wandering around
like that,
...I came across an old man in North America
who used to be a sailor.
北米で
元船乗りの老人に出会ったんです
The stars were bright
and clear that night.
星がよく出てました
The old man laughed
at my questions.
私の疑問は
老人に笑われてしまいました
“お若い方―”
He said, "Young man, you try too hard to put
everything into clear-cut categories."
“あなたは物事を 何でも
はっきりさせようとしすぎる”って
ああ… うん 九太郎君
Kyutaro-kun, where do you think the boundary
is between the Earth and space?
宇宙と地球の境目って
どの辺だと思う？
ああ… それは 上空熱圏
100キロメートルくらいから―
Well, there's a sharp drop in atmospheric density
up past 100km in the upper thermosphere.
急激に大気密度が減って
200キロメートルくらいからが…
Then at 200km,
there's...
（ユーリ）うーん…
私の感じでは
ないんですよね 境目が
The way I see it, there isn't one.
There is no boundary.
No. There are no boundaries
in the world.
うん ないんだ
世界に境目なんて
なんか それでいいと思いますよ
I think that is how
it should be.
フッ… 実を言うとね
この形見を見つけたら―
To tell you the truth, I had planned to quit being
a debris hauler once I found this compass.
デブリ屋を
辞めようと思っていたんです
これを見つけ出すこと以外で
宇宙に居続ける理由がなかったから
Because aside from finding this,
I had no reason to stay in space.
But perhaps what that
old man said is correct.
でも やっぱり あの老人の
言うとおりかもしれません
ん？
Space... The Earth... Guideposts...
宇宙とか 地球とか
道しるべとか―
Senpai! Too far!
宇宙とか 地球とか
道しるべとか―
（タナベ）先輩 行き過ぎ
（ハチマキ）ああっ？
宇宙とか 地球とか
道しるべとか―
ほら あそこ
（ハチマキ）あっ ああ
Look over there!
ほら あそこ
（ハチマキ）あっ ああ
あまり関係ないみたいです
Those things don't seem all that important.
And so... Thank you for
breaking my compass.
だから コンパス壊してくれて
ありがとうね
（九太郎）ああ…
うーん… よく分かんね
I don't really
understand.
実は 私にも
よく分かってないんです
To tell you the truth, I don't really get it either.
アハハハ…
（タナベ）ユーリさーん
Yuri-san!
（ハチマキ）
何やってんだ？ そんなとこで
What're you doing
out here?
（ユーリ）ああ すいません
Sorry.
Come, let's go back. It is quite cold here.
もう 帰りましょう
さすがに寒い あっ…
Kyutaro-kun, would you mind
doing something for me?
九太郎君
ちょっと お願いしていいかな？
♪～
Here.
（ハチマキ）ほれ
あっ ありがとうございます
Thanks.
Sorry I'm late.
（ユーリ）遅くなっちゃって
（ハチマキ）ん？
Damn it, Kyutaro's rocket bug
has gotten even worse...
九太郎のやつ
ロケット病が悪化しやがってよ
食事中もいじってんだぜ
He was even fiddling around
with it at the dinner table!
へえ
We have completed
our takeoff sequence.
（アナウンス）離陸シークエンスを
終了いたしました
We are now beginning our atmospheric
flight sequence,
当機はこれより 赤道までの
圏内飛行シークエンスに…
...which will last until
we reach the equator.
It should be any time now.
さて そろそろか
Also, we ask that all passengers
remain in their seats...
For what? See something?
何が？ 何か見えんの？
あっ うちの辺り？
...until the flight crew says that it
is safe to move about the cabin.
Isn't that near my house?
えっ 先輩の家(うち)が見えるんですか？
What, can we see your
house from here?
やった！
（ハチマキ）ああっ！？
He did it!
Oh, man, that little maniac
did it...
ありゃあ
やりやがった あいつ
Kyutaro-kun is pretty amazing,
isn't he?
If he keeps this up, people are
gonna think he's a terrorist...
こんなことして
テロと間違われるぞ
あれのフェアリングにな
Want to know what's
in its nose cone?
（ハチマキ･タナベ）えっ？
俺のコンパスが入ってるんだ
My compass
is in there.
（タナベ）あ…
Yuri? You're...
ユーリ お前…
You seem different.
なんか変わった？
フッ…
No big deal. I'll catch up
with him soon enough.
（九太郎）
なあに すぐに追いつくさ
♪～
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Turning Point
Next Time
It's an order from the
assistant manager.
（エーデル）
係長補佐命令
（ラビィ）
社内恋愛を禁止する！
Office romances
are prohibited!
（リュシー）えっ！
フンッ 心の狭い親父だな
This is one
narrow-minded dad.
（リュシー）
チェンシンさん
Cheng-Shin-san?
（ハチマキ）するか？
Do you want to do it?
はい！
Excuse me?!
寝たの？
（ラビィ）はい！
Have you slept with him?
Excuse me?!
（ハチマキ）
ちゃんと最後まで…
All the way...
はい！
（フィー）うるさい！
Excuse me?!
Shut up!
（課長）
ああっ… 何か言った？
Did you say something?
（ハチマキ）
嫌み言うなよ
Don't get so
sarcastic on me!
性格ブスですから
I can't help it. I'm ugly
on the inside, after all.
うん かわいそうだよねえ
Right, I feel sorry
for them.
課長補佐命令
It's an order from the assistant
section chief.